Finding Aid for the Lejaren Hiller Collection of Audio Tape Recordings, 1958-1985
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Algorithms Cycle (H. 42, 48, 67), undated, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Version 4; "This tape contains substitution of performance by Salvatore Martirano (a) of just "Quotations and Phraseology", (b) of all 3 movements of version 4 of Algorithms III." Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 243)
  Algorithms I: (1) The Decay of Information (2) Icosahedron (3) The Incorporation of Constraints Algorithms II: (1) Campanology Algorithms III: (1) Refinements (2) Quotations and Phraseology (3) Synthesis
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Algorithms Cycle (H. 42, 48, 67), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, DBX; Master tape Versions 1 and 3 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 244)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Algorithms Cycle (H. 42, 48, 67), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, DBX; Master tape Version 2; Program notes for Algorithms Cycle included with tape Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 245)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Algorithms Cycle (H. 42, 48, 67), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Tail out; Cue tapes "6" leader between movements; 3" leader within movements." Version 1 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 246)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Algorithms Cycle (H. 42, 48, 67), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Tail out; Cue tapes "6" leader between movements; 3" leader within movements." Version 2 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 247)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Algorithms Cycle (H. 42, 48, 67), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Tail out; Cue tapes "6" leader between movements; 3" leader within movements." Version 3 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 248)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Algorithms (IV), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips (1st movement), 7 ½ ips (all others)DBX; [Presumably version 4 of Algorithms cycle] Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 249)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Fast and slow, for saxophone quartet (1984) (H. 68), undated, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Only recording Duration: 17:30 (H. 68); 11:53 (H. 69); 5:00 (H. 70) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 250)
  I. Presto Furioso 8:00 II. Adagio Espressivo 9:26
  H. 69, Expo '85, for multiple synthesizers (1985), composed with Charles Ames and John Myhill I. Circus Piece 4:04 II. Transitions 2:12 III. Toy Harmonium 1:41 IV. Mix or Match (5 example) 3:44
  H. 70, The fox trots again, for chamber ensemble (1985) I. Relaxed Swing Tempo
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Expo '85, for multiple synthesizers (1985), composed with Charles Ames and John Myhill (H. 69), undated, 1 10 inch reel; speed unknown, DBX; Master tape Duration: 11:53 (H. 69) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 251)
  I. Circus Dance 4:04 II. Transitions 2:12 III. Toy Harmonium 1:41 IV. Mix or Match (5 Examples) 3:44
  "Back up tape duplicating the above + 3 other examples of mix or match items."
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Expo '85, for multiple synthesizers (1985), composed with Charles Ames and John Myhill (H. 69), undated, 1 10 inch reel; speed unknown; "Hiller Rehearsal Tape" Notes on reel: "2 extra copies of "Expo 85" - 2nd copy with extra mix or match tunes." Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 252)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Fox trots again, for chamber ensemble (1985) (H. 70), undated, 1 7 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo., Tail out; Only performance of H. 70 Performers: H. 70: Buffalo New Music Ensemble; H. 71: Buffalo Guitar Quartet Duration: 5:00 (H. 70); 6:00 (H. 71) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 253)
  H. 71, Metaphors, for guitar quartet (1986)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Metaphors, for guitar quartet (1986) (H. 71), undated, 1 7 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Dolby A; Master tapes Master tape for H. 71 2 copies: Copy 1 - flawed by some noise about ½ way through Copy 2 - excellent - used for copies Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 254)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Three electronic pieces, undated, 1 10 inch reel, ½ inch reel tape; speed unknown, 4-channel quadraphonic; Part of H. 64 "4-channel master work tapes for 3 Electronic Pieces: "I'll tell you how", etc. Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 255)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata no. 1 for violin and piano, H. 7, undated, 1 10 inch reel; speed unknown; Collective title on container: Chamber music, volume 3: Music for violin and piano Performers: Various performers Duration: 19:42; 16:30; 15:30; 6:41 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 256)
  H. 18a, Sonata no. 2 for violin and piano
  H. 45, Sonata no. 3 for violin and piano
  H. 50, Six easy pieces for violin and piano
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Fantasy for three pianos, H. 14, undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Collective title on container: Chamber music, volume 4: Music for 2 or more pianos Performers: Various performers Duration: 15:34; 18:38; [18:00] Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 257)
  H. 39, Suite for two pianos and tape
  H. 46, A Cenotaph for two pianos
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Algorithms I, H. 42, undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo., Tail out; Collective title on container: Chamber music, volume 6 Performers: Various performers Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 258)
  H. 48, Algorithms II
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Portfolio, for diverse performers and tapes (1974), H. 51, undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Collective title on container: Chamber music, volume 7 Performers: Various performers Duration: [22:00?] 10:48; 11:52 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 259)
  H. 52, Malta, for tuba and tape
  H. 56, Persiflage, for flute, oboe and percussion
  H. 58, Diabelskie skrzypce, for stringed instruments and harpsichord
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Symphony no. 2, H. 28, undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, Full-track mono.; Collective title on container: Orchestral music Performers: Various performers Duration: 38:34; 9:50 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 260)
  H. 53, A preview of coming attractions
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Symphony no. 2, H. 28, undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, Full-track mono.; Collective title on container: Orchestral Music - storage tapes Storage tapes Duplicate of Tape 260 Performers: Various performers Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 261)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata no. 1 for piano, H. 1, undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Collective title on container: Piano music, volume 1 Performers: Various performers Duration: 28:15; 23:55 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 262)
  H. 4, Seven artifacts
  H.8, Processional
  H. 9, Fugue
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Twelve-tone variations, H. 17, undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips; Collective title on container: Piano music, volume 3 Performers: Various performers Duration: 30:49; 3:48; 15:06 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 263)
  H. 19, Two theater pieces
  H. 23, Scherzo for piano
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata no. 4 for piano, H. 11, undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo., Tail out; 7 ½ ips copies of master tapes with Dolby noise suppression removed; Collective title on container: Piano music, volume 4 Performers: Various performers Duration: 29:20; 26:00 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 264)
  H. 29, Sonata no. 5 for piano
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Sonata no. 6 for piano, H. 47, undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Collective title on container: Piano music, volume 5 Performers: Various performers Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 265)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Jesse James, for vocal quartet and piano, H. 10, undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Collective title on container: Vocal music Performers: Various performers Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 266)
  H. 24, Five Appalachian ballads for voice and guitar
  H. 36, Computer cantata
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Portfolio, for diverse performers and tape, H. 51, Recorded May 1, 1977, 1 10 inch reel; speed unknown; Collective title on container: Vocal music, volume 2 Performers: Gregg Smith Singers, conducted by Gregg Smith Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 267)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Music for a "dream play", H. 21, Recorded June 21, 1972, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Collective title on container: Theater music, volume 1 Performers: Production by the Buffalo Theater Workshop in cooperation with the Center of the Creative and Performing Arts directed by Terry Moore; orchestra directed by Jan Williams. "Complete performance of the play by August Strindberg." - Continued on Tape 269. Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 268)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Music for a "dream play", H. 21. Part Two, Act two, H. 22 recorded 1958, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo. (H. 21) and full-track mono. (H. 22), Tail out; Collective title on container: Theater music, volume 2 Performers: Production by the Buffalo Theater Workshop in cooperation with the Center of the Creative and Performing Arts directed by Terry Moore; orchestra directed by Jan Williams. H. 22: Production by University Theater, University of Illinois directed by Clara Be H: 22 "Complete performance of the play by Aristophanes as adapted by Walter Kerr" - Continued on Tape 270. Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 269)
  H. 22, Music for "The birds"
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Music for "The birds", conclusion, Recorded 1958, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, full-track mono., Tail out; Collective title on container: Theater music, volume 3 Performers: Production by University Theater, University of Illinois directed by Clara Behringer; Chamber ensemble conducted by Lejaren Hiller. Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 270)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Music for a "dream play", H. 21, undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, full-track mono.; Collective title on container: Theater music, volume 4 Performers: Ensemble conducted by Lejaren Hiller "This is the "suite" version of the music which is slightly different from the music as cued for the Strindberg play." Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 271)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Electronic music for "Blue is the antecedent of it", H. 26, H. 27: recorded July 10, 1975, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Collective title on container: Theater music, volume 5 Performers: H. 27: Tess Spangler, Anne Gayley, Gary Burke, David Lamb, directed by Elizabeth Hiller H. 26: music only Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 272)
  H. 27, Cuthbert Bound
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Triptych for Hieronymus, H. 38, undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Collective title on container: Theater music, volume 8 Performers: Ensemble conducted by Jan Williams Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 273)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Dream play, by August Strindberg, with original music by Lejaren Hiller. Act I, Recorded June 21, 1972, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Performers: Various performers Complete performance of play, with incidental music? Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 274)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Dream play, by August Strindberg, with original music by Lejaren Hiller. Act II, undated, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Performers: Various performers Complete performance of play, with incidental music? Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 275)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Spoon River, Illinois, H. 34, Recorded December 1, 1977, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Collective title on container: American Music Theater: with music by Lejaren Hiller Performers: Various performers Duration: 26:24; 25:16; 26:54 Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 276)
  H. 33, Music for "The man with the oboe"
  H.57, Ponteach
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Music for "The man with the oboe", H. 33 (H. 33), "Combined version", 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips; Storage copies Performers: Ensembles conducted by John Garvey and James Kasprowicz Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 277)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Rage over the lost Beethoven. Part I (H. 47b), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo.; Duplicate Performers: Stephen Manes, piano Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 278)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Rage over the lost Beethoven. Part II (H. 47b), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo.; Duplicate Performers: Stephen Manes, piano Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 279)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Rage over the lost Beethoven. Part III (H. 47b), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo.; Duplicate Performers: Michael Collier, Roger Shields, piano Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 280)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Algorithms I, for nine instruments and tape (Versions I and IV) (H. 42), undated, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Dolby A 301 stretched, Tail out; Master Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 281)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Triptych for Hieronymus (H. 38), Recorded February 17, 1973, 1 10 inch reel; 15 ips, 2-channel stereo., Dolby A 301 stretched; Sub-master Duplicate of Master tape 84 Performers: Theater Orchestra conducted by Jan Williams See Tape 84 (Master) Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 282)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Jesse James, A Ballad for Vocal Quartet and Upright Piano (1950), H. 10, Recorded July 6, 1973, 1 10 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo., Tail out; Collective title on container: Program of Musical Americana Performers: H. 10: performed by Jane Bane, Marjorie Rosenberg, Keith Daniel, Andrew Schultze (vocal quartet), and Jane Cary, piano; H. 34 performed by Kathie Baldwin, Rick Fanning, Patrick Murphy, Thom Neeson, Mary Schweitzer, Susan Wehle, Robin Willoughby, actors; Camille Krenglicki, Andrew Stiller, Beye Fyfe, David Sussman, Robert Previte, Lorin Pearson, conducted by Lejaren Hiller; H. 24a performed by Winifred Black, soprano, and David Sussman, guitar; H. 40 performed by Carl Kowalkowski, pitchman, Marjorie Rosenberg, Robert Previte, Clifford Stoll, Gail Chandler, Lory Cohen. Tape digitally reformatted: Yes (Item 283)
  H. 34. Spoon River, Illinois" for narrators and instrumental sextet
  H. 24a. Five Appalachian Ballads for Voice and Guitar (1958)
  H. 40, An avalanche for pitchman
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Harmonic tone generator demonstration tape: Improvisations with harmonic tone generator; Five modulations, 1963, 1 7 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo., Tail out; Fourteen examples from various composers. Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 284)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Electronic music lecture tape, undated, 1 7 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, 2-channel stereo.; Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 285)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Computer music composition lecture examples, undated, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Examples from Hiller's works, including Electronic sonata, Illiac suite, HPSCHD, Persiflage, and Expo 85 (complete). Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 286)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Supplementary computer composition lecture tape, undated, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Examples from Hiller's works, including Illiac suite, Computer cantata, Avalanche, HPSCHD, Algorithms I, II, and III, Computer music, Preview of coming attractions, and Persiflage. Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 287)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Lecture 7: Illiac suite (complete); Two excerpts from The birds, undated, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 288)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 Lecture 10 tape: Expo '85 for multiple synthesizers (with extra tunes); The fox trots again, undated, 1 7 inch reel; speed unknown; Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 289)
- Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994 CSX-1 sound synthesis demonstration tape, undated, 1 7 inch reel; 7 ½ ips, full track; Tape digitally reformatted: No (Item 290)
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Subjects
Hiller, Lejaren, 1924-1994--Archives; Computer music; Electronic music
Genres
Sound recordings; Audiotapes
Associated Material
Related Resources
Related Resources in the Music Library
Lejaren Hiller Archive
Mus. Arc. 5
Music manuscripts, including sketches, program notes, correspondence, writings, and photographs.
Lejaren Hiller Collection of Compositional Flow Charts, circa 1968-1987
Mus. Arc. 5.3
Flow charts created for computer music composition by Lejaren Hiller and included as figures and illustrations in his published articles about the processes used in writing computer music, including his works, HPSCHD, Algorithms I and Algorithms III. The collection also contains unidentified flow charts and diagrams, as well as negatives of other charts created by Hiller.
Lejaren A. Hiller: Computer Music Pioneer
Online exhibit summary about Lejaren Hiller utilizing materials from the Lejaren Hiller Archive.